本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on The Bible...
犹太王国是由伟大的英雄们一手建立
Great heroes have forged the Jewish nation in faith.
诺厄拯救地上的生物免遭洪水
Noah saved life on earth from the flood.
天主警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
亚巴郎成为万民之父
Abraham became the father of God's nation.
亚巴郎
Abraham!
梅瑟解放子民  带他们摆脱埃及人的奴役
Moses freed the people from Egyptian slavery.
主啊
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
然后  他颁布了天主的法律
Then, he delivered God's laws.
我们有可以助我们夺下盟约之地的新法律了
We have new laws preparing us for the Promised Land.
伟大的达味王团结以色列人
The great King David united the Israelites...
以色列
Israel!
攻下了耶路撒冷
and won the city of Jerusalem.
但因被超级大国围困
But surrounded by superpowers,
以色列一直为自身的存亡不断抗争
Israel's survival was a constant struggle.
然后罗马帝国攻占了盟约之地
Then Rome conquered the Promised Land.
人们渴望一位新的达味王——一位救世主
People long for a new King David, a savior.
有人认为那人便是洗者若翰
Some believed it was John the Baptist.
你已洁净  所有以色列人也将和你一样
As you are cleansed, so all Israel shall be cleansed.
人们都成群结队去找那个野人似的若翰
People are flocking to this wild man, John.
他们认为他是先知
They think he's a prophet.
我只是旷野里的声音
I am just a voice in the wilderness,
预备上主的...
preparing the way for the...
...道路
...Lord.
为我施洗吧
Baptize me!
他将带来正义与公平的新时代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice.
他的力量将带领人类迈向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world.
全人类
All people!
耶稣开始召叫门徒
Jesus has started to gather disciples
他们放弃一切跟从他
who give up everthing to follow him.
来跟从我  伯多禄
Come with me, Peter.
别再捕鱼了  我要使你们成为渔人的渔夫
Give up catching fish and I will make you a fisher of men.
如今他们与惧怕所有异教的
Now they are on a collision cause
当局站在了对立的一面
with the temple of authorities who fear any Dissent.
我收到关于一个年轻先知——纳匝肋人耶稣的报告
I've had a report of a young prophet, Jesus of Nazareth.
而罗马人  绝不会容忍此事
And Romans, who won't tolerate.
是时候让你们明白  主人为你们做了什么
It's time you understood what your masters do for you.
-我们要做什么  -改变世界
- What are we going to do? - Change the world.
圣经
加里肋亚
在加里肋亚这个穷乡僻壤的地方  巨变要来了
In the poor backwater of Galilee, revolution is coming.
世世代代的以色列人都受
For generations, the people of Israel have been guided
犹太教守护者法利塞人的指引
by the Pharisees, guardians of the Jewish faith.
你们应谨慎遵守上主你们天主所吩咐你的
You should untiringly keep the commandments
诫命，教训和法令
of the Lord your God and his statutes...
法利塞人相信民族的福祉
The Pharisees believe the well-being of the nation
在于严格遵守天主给梅瑟的法律
depends on strictly observing the laws God gave to Moses.
他们深受人们爱戴
They are loved and admired by the people.
你们应做上主眼中视为正义
You should do what is right and what is good
和美善的事
in sight of the Lord.
你看见他了吗  就在那里
Have you seen him? Over there!
但耶稣提供了一种新的方式
But Jesus offers a new way...
那时，上主吩咐我们遵守这一切法令...
So the Lord commanded us to observe all these statutes...
是耶稣
It's Jesus!
这边  若望 一直往前走不要停
This way, John. Keep everyone moving.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
我们以什么来比拟天主的国呢？
How shall we picture the kingdom of God?
它好像一粒芥子
It is like a mustard seed...
种在地里的时候
...which a man took and sowed in his field,
比地上一切的种子都小.
the smallest seed in the world.
当下种之后...
Yet when planted...
...生长出来...
...it grows up...
...比一切蔬菜都大.
...and becomes the biggest of all plants.
接着呢
What's going on?
并且长出大枝，以致天上的飞鸟能
It becomes a tree where birds can come...
他瘫了
He's paralyzed.
...栖息在它的荫下
... and make their nests.
孩子，你的罪赦了.
Your sins are forgiven, my son.
你们听到了吗
Did you hear that?
他赦了他的罪
He has forgiven his sins.
不是只有天主才能赦罪吗
I thought only God could do that?
这不是亵渎吗
Isn't that blasphemy?
他懂得的  这就是亵渎
He knows. It is blasphemy.
你是这意思吗  我的朋友
Is that your wish, my friend?
回答我啊
Well, answer me.
告诉我什么比较容易呢...
Tell me which is easier...
是说：他的罪赦了
...to say his sins are forgiven,
或是说...
or say...
起来行走吧？
Get up and walk?
等等...
Wait...
人子在地上有赦罪的权柄.
The Son of Man has authority to forgive sin.
朋友们
Friends!
什么事
What is this about?
连梅瑟都不会觉得自己能够赦他人的罪
Not even Moses himself would've thought he could forgive sin.
你听到老师是怎么说了
You heard what our teacher said.
他到底凭什么权柄可以这么做
On what authority does he think he can do this?
凭他自己的权柄
On his authority.
这是亵渎
That is blasphemy.
只有天主才可以赦罪
Only God can forgive sin.
而你的朋友
And your friend
这样说可能会被石头打死的
could be stoned for a false claim like this.
这不过才开始罢了
This is just the beginning.
我们走
Let's go.
随着门徒的增多
With a growing number of disciples,
耶稣从这个城走到那个城
Jesus moves from town to town,
讲述着天国的道理 并不断显神迹
teaching about god's kingdom and working miracles.
不洁  污秽  他是一个癞病人
Unclean, unclean. He's a Leper!
都避开他
Get away from him!
求你了  求你了...
Please, please...
别碰他
Don't touch him!
我洁净了  我洁净了  我洁净了
I'm clean, I'm clean. I'm clean!
对有些人来说  耶稣是救世主
Jesus is a savior to some...
看他都做了什么
Look what he's done!
但对罗马  他却是个潜在威胁
...but a potential threat to Rome.
新任罗马总督般雀·比拉多
The new Roman governor is Pontius Pilate,
过去是军人  如今成了一位残酷的政客
an ex-soldier turned ruthless politician.
停  怎么了
Halt! What's going on?
你们挡着路了  总督要过去
You're in the way! The Governor needs to pass.
比拉多可不会等
Pilate won't wait!
还要等很久吗
Will it be much longer?
很快就好  亲爱的
Very soon, my love.
-长官  -这次因何停下
- Prefect... - What's the delay this time?
道中有辆破车  长官
It's a broken cart, sir.
那你们还等什么  给我处理掉
What are you waiting for? Get it off the road!
搬开  搬开
Let's get it moved! Move it!
比拉多统治下的犹太人濒临爆发
Rebellion simmers amongst Pilate's Jewish subjects,
但他不允许任何破坏罗马统治
but he allows nothing to disrupt Roman rule...
和罗马税收的举动
...or Roman taxes.
所有税款必须缴清
All taxes must be paid in full!
我们同为犹太人  他们怎能如此
We're all Jews. How can they live with themselves?
自己人却为罗马人卖命  真让人厌恶
Our own people working for Rome? These people makes me sick.
同流合污之徒  我们走吧
Collaborators. Let's move on.
都是些蠹虫
They're stinking vermin.
你应该离他们远一点
You should keep your distance from them.
有两个人
Two men...
上圣殿去祈祷
... went to the temple to pray.
一个是法利塞人
One a Pharisee...
而另一个
... and the other one
是个税吏
a tax collector.
法利塞人祈祷说 天主
The Pharisee prayed: God...
我感谢你  因为我不像其他的人
I thank you that I'm not like other men,
偷盗  奸淫
thieves, adulterers...
也不像这个税吏...
... or this tax collector.
但那税吏
But the tax collector
连举目望天都不敢
didn't even look up to heaven.
他说
He said,
天主
God...
可怜我
have mercy on me,
这个罪人吧
I'm a sinner.
天主祝福了那个税吏...
God blessed the tax collector...
而不是法利塞人
not the Pharisee.
因为凡高举自己的  必被贬抑
Anyone who praises himself will be humbled,
凡贬抑自己的  必被高举
and anyone who humbles himself will be praised.
玛窦  跟随我
Matthew...come.
看  现在他甚至叫罪人跟随他
See, now he even calls the sinners to follow him!
让人不禁好奇  他的其他追随者
One has to wonder of the sins committed
都犯了什么罪行
by his other followers.
税吏
Tax collectors!
他们心中都没有一丝善意
There's not a thread of good in any of them.
多默   耶稣不是为义人而来
Thomas, Jesus has not come for the good,
而是为罪人而来
but for the sinners.
他给人们第二次机会
He gives people a second chance.
我们也应该这样
We should too.
神贫的人是有福的
Blessed are the poor,
《圣经》原文为 Blessed are the poor in spirit 取自主宣讲的真福八端
因为天国是他们的
for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
温良的人是有福的
Blessed are the meek,
因为他们要承受土地
for they shall inherit the earth.
心里洁净的人是有福的
Blessed are the pure in heart,
因为他们要看见天主
for they shall see God.
你们向他祈祷 他必会聆听
Pray to him and he will listen.
我们应如何祈祷
And how should we pray?
像这样
Like this.
我们的天父
Our Father who is in heaven,
愿你的名受显扬
hallowed be your name.
愿你的国来临
Your kingdom come,
愿你的旨意
your will be done,
奉行在人间  如同在天上
on earth as it is in heaven.
求您今天赏给我们  日用的食粮
Give us this day our daily bread.
求您宽恕我们的罪过
And forgive us our trespasses,
如同我们宽恕别人一样
as we forgive those who trespass against us.
用石头打死她  她是个淫妇
Stone her! She's a whore!
大家都知道经上是怎么说的
You know what it says in the Scriptures.
-这里  -母亲
- Here! - Mother!
救我
Please!
-淫妇  -躲开点
- Adulteress! -Go away.
法律命令我们
The law commands us
用石头砸死这样的妇人
to stone such a woman.
你怎么看
What do you say?
这是个陷阱
It's a trap.
我会把我的石头
I'll give my stone
给第一个敢对我说
to the first man who tells me
自己从未犯过罪的人
that he has never sinned.
谢谢你  谢谢你
Thank you, thank you.
去罢，从今以后不要再犯罪了
Go, and sin no more.
不能再这样下去了
This cannot continue.
他嘲弄我们的法律
He ridicules our laws,
侮辱我们祖先的传统
insults the traditions of our fathers.
我们苦苦奋斗来的一切
Everything that we have fought so hard for,
我们的信仰
our faith,
我们的社会
our communities,
天主赐予我们的一切
everything God has given.
圣殿  耶路撒冷
-盖法  -尼苛德摩
- Caiaphas! - Nicodemus.
我收到关于一个年轻先知的报告
I've had a report of a young prophet,
纳匝肋人耶稣
a Jesus of Nazareth.
他在加里肋亚有一大批追随者
He has a big following in Galilee.
传闻说他会来耶路撒冷
It's rumored he'll come to Jerusalem.
加里肋亚
Galilee?
-他能显神迹  -都这么吹
- He works miracles. - They all do.
尼苛德摩  别担心
Nicodemus, don't worry,
来自加里肋亚的从来都是小事
nothing important ever came from Galilee!
加里肋亚海
耶稣  耶稣
Jesus! Jesus!
这里像个清静地方
Looks like a quiet place.
可以了
That's it.
-拴上  -辣彼  我来帮你
- Lock it off. - Rabbi, let me help you.
有几千人之多
There are thousands of them.
这些都是追随者
These are the followers.
他们历经长途跋涉  天色不早了
They've come a long way. It's late.
他们说他们饿了
They say they're hungry.
给他们些食物
Give them food.
拿什么给
But how?
我们一无所有  只有些鱼和面包
We have nothing. Just a few fish and some bread.
把它们给我
Bring them to me.
天父  感谢你带给我们的
Thank you, Father, for what you bring us.
我们的天父哺育天空中的飞鸟
Our father in heaven feeds the birds of the air.
他会给你们多少
How much more will he give to you?
不用担心日常所需  天主必会赏给我们
Don't worry about daily needs, God will provide.
把天主放在第一位  其他一切都将成就
Put God first and everything else will follow.
倘若你渴望公义
If you hunger for righteousness,
你将通过我感受到
you will be filled through me.
他说你们求
He said ask...
就会得到
...and it will be given.
来自天主的
From God.
来自天主的  这是来自天主的
From God. It's from God!
默西亚  默西亚
Messiah! Messiah!
他们希望你做他们的王  犹太人的君王
They want you to be their king. King of the Jews!
你可以如军队般带领我们
You can lead us like an army.
我们有能力击败罗马人
We are strong enough to beat the Romans!
不  不应该通过这种方式
No, this is not the way.
不应通过武力
Not by force.
他要去哪儿  怎么回事
Where is he going? What's wrong?
有五千人前往见他
Five thousand came to see him.
五千人
Five thousand.
现在他们高喊着 "默西亚"
Now they shout, "Messiah."
今天那些人民  他们称你为"王"
The people today, they called you "King",
他们认为你是默西亚
they think you are a Messiah.
但你似乎没理会他们
But you seemed to ignore them.
你不会做我们的君王吗
Aren't you going to be our king?
你们说我是谁
Who do you think I am?
永生天主之子
You are the Son of God.
伯多禄  你是有福的 因为不是肉和血启示了你
You can't have known this by what you know of me, Peter.
而是我在天之父
It has been revealed to you by God.
你是伯多禄（磐石）
You are Peter,
在这磐石上，我要建立我的教会
and on this rock I will build my church.
明日我会在对岸等你们
Tomorrow I'll meet you on the other shore.
为何他要在我们壮大时离开
Why did he walk away just when we're getting strong?
救世主是不会这样离开我们的
Surely a Messiah wouldn't leave us like this.
默西亚应该是位勇士
A Messiah should be a warrior,
像达味一样的征服者
a conqueror like David.
犹达斯  暴力不是解决的方式
Judas! Force is not the way.
那么告诉我默西亚的方式什么
So tell me what the way of the Messiah is?
他与众不同
He's different.
但是玛丽亚  倘若他不是默西亚呢
But Mary, what if he's not the one?
我们冒着生命危险  为了什么
We're risking our lives, for what?
他展示给我们了他的能力
He has shown us his power.
我们要对他有信心
We must have faith in him.
-来吧  -他不会让我们失望
- Come on. - He'll not fail us.
他说他会在对面等我们  走吧
He said he'd meet us on the other side. Let's go!
把帆放下
Bring the sail down!
把东西都系紧
Tie everything down!
这太危险了
This is too dangerous!
我们应趁来得及转头回去
We should turn back while we still can.
你也听见他说的话了  他希望我们能过去
You heard what he said, he wants us to cross.
那是什么
What is that?
是个妖怪
It's a ghost!
不  多默
No, Thomas.
是耶稣
It's Jesus.
他就是默西亚
He is the Messiah!
伯多禄
Peter...
伯多禄  你在做什么
Peter, what are you doing?
不要怕
Don't be afraid.
过来
Come.
伯多禄
Peter!
不
No!
伯多禄
Peter...
小信德的人啊
You of little faith.
你为什么怀疑
Why did you doubt?
你必须坚定不移
You need to be strong.
纳匝肋
玛丽亚  他回来了
Mary! He's here!
-谁  -耶稣  他终于回来了
- Who? - Jesus! He's back at last.
自从天使加俾额尔造访耶稣的母亲
Ever since the Angel Gabriel came to Jesus' mother,
她就知晓了儿子真正的使命
she's known her son's true purpose.
现在  人们也即将知晓
It's time for others to learn.
耶稣在会堂里朗诵了一段
In the synagogue, Jesus reads
当时广为流传的经文之一
from one of the most popular scriptures of the time,
该经文预言了默西亚的降临
a prophecy describing the coming of the Messiah.
上主的神临于我身上
The Spirit of the Lord is upon me,
因为他给我傅了油
because he has anointed me
派遣我向贫穷人传报喜讯
to preach good news to the poor.
向俘虏宣告释放
He has sent me to declare freedom for the captives,
向盲者宣告复明
and recovery of sight for the blind,
使受压迫者获得自由
to set free those who are oppressed.
今天
Today...
这经文应验了
...this scripture is fulfilled.
你说什么
What are you saying?
你说你已经完成了那些使命
That you have achieved all this?
你说你就是被天主选中派来人间的默西亚吗
That you are the Messiah, the chosen one sent by God?
不可能
No!
我是说你们应顺从天主的旨意
I'm saying you must accept God's word.
大胆  你这是亵渎神灵
How dare you? That is sacrilege.
他从未修习过法律  无知得很
He has never studied the law. This man knows nothing!
他的医治能力源自魔鬼
His healing is the work of demons!
预言开始应验了
It has begun.
他破坏了我们的信仰
He undermines our faith!
-他甚至招募淫乱的信徒  -伯多禄
- He recruits adulterers... - Peter!
那边的脸也由他打
Turn the other cheek.
你会为此付出代价
You'll pay the price for this!
正如你的朋友洗者若翰一样
Like your friend, John the Baptist!
你还没有听说吧
You haven't heard, have you?
他已被处死
He was executed.
身首异处
Beheaded!
-他是个好人  -是的  但却死了
- He was a good man. - Yes, and now he's dead.
请为我施洗
Baptize me.
若翰是我见过最好的良师
John was the greatest teacher I ever knew.
他不仅仅是先知
He was more than a prophet.
我们的使命还要继续
Our work goes on.
过些日子我们就去耶路撒冷
Soon we go to Jerusalem.
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem?
-操之过急  -也太危险
- It's too soon. - It's too dangerous.
我们还没准备好
We're not ready.
犹达斯  我们为何聚集于此
Judas, why are we all here?
为了走康庄大道吗
To take the easy path?
我们必须把讯息带到耶路撒冷
We must take the message to Jerusalem.
直插王权的心脏
Right to the heart of power.
耶路撒冷
比拉多的宅邸
总督大人  我们需要您  有麻烦了
Prefect, you're needed. There's trouble.
罗马渣滓  罗马强盗  要他们好看
Roman scum! Roman thieves! Let's show them!
罗马强盗
Roman thieves!
为大司祭让路
Make way for the high priest!
玛耳曷  玛耳曷  发生何事
Malchus! Malchus, what's happening?
又发生了抗议  大司祭
It's another protest, high priest.
我们得带您离开这儿  抗议正衍变成暴动
We need to get you out of here, it's turning into a riot.
将大人送回宅邸  越快越好
Get the master back to his residence. Quick as you can!
-怎么回事  -是水沟惹的祸
- What is all this about? - The aqueduct.
罗马人动用了我们的圣殿基金去挖水沟
The people are furious that the Romans used our temple funds
民众非常愤怒
to build it.
上百民众正要去向比拉多告状
Hundreds are heading to complain to Pilate.
什么
What?
他们尚未近身就会被下令斩杀
He'll have them cut down before they can get anywhere near him.
他曾承诺会听取民众的不满
He said he'd listen to their grievances.
这是个圈套  尼苛德摩  你看不出来吗
It's a trap, Nicodemus! Can't you see that?
强盗  人渣
Thieves! Scum!
罗马人渣
Roman scum!
耶路撒冷需要水
Jerusalem needs water.
你们觉得水是你们的天主带来的吗
You think your God brings it?
不  不是他
No, he does not.
是我们罗马人带来的
Rome does.
是时候让你们明白
It's time you understood
你们的主人为你们做了什么
what your masters do for you!
比拉多这是要我们守本分
Pilate's keeping us in our place.
否则设想一下他会在逾越节做出什么事来
Imagine what he could do at Passover.
伯达尼村
玛尔大  出什么事了
Martha, what's wrong?
我兄弟死了
My brother is dead.
你来得太晚了
You're too late.
带我去他的墓穴看看
Show me the tomb.
他死去多久了
How long has he been dead?
已经四天了
He's been there four days.
拉匝禄...
Lazarus...
我就是复活...
I am the resurrection...
就是生命
...and the life.
凡信从我的...
Anyone who believes in me...
即使死了...
...even if he dies...
仍要活着
...he will still have life.
拉匝禄
Lazarus!
我的兄弟啊
My brother, oh!
凡活着信我的人必永远不死
Whoever believes in me shall never die.
如果你信，就会看到天主的光荣
Believe in me and you will see the glory of God.
盖法
Caiaphas!
有人说那个耶稣把一个死人救活了
They say this Jesus has raised a man from the dead.
什么
What?
他会来耶路撒冷过逾越节
He will be here in Jerusalem for Passover.
不行
No.
但如果他与万千拥护者相伴而来
But if he comes with thousands of supporters,
随着庆祝节日的人们相继到来
the city will already be breaking at the seams
这城将会人满为患
with those arriving for the festival.
尼苛德摩 你说得对
Nicodemus, you are right.
到时罗马人就会插手了
The Romans will step in.
我们必须阻止这个神棍  这个骗子
We must not allow this miracle man, this fraud,
来破坏逾越节
to disrupt Passover.
这事比拉多知道吗
Does Pilate know?
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on the Bible
他现在在哪儿
Where is he now?
他刚骑着驴...进了城门
He's just entered the gate. On a donkey.
长官  一个犹太人正在圣殿里制造麻烦
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
-他说什么  -将来没有一块石头是不被拆毁的
- He said what?  - Not one stone will be left standing.
毁了这殿  我会在三日之内重新建立起来
Destroy this temple and I will build it again in three days.
如果一场骚乱
If the disturbances that took place a day
在第二天依然继续的话
are repeated tomorrow,
我将立刻关闭圣殿
I will shut the temple immediately.
取消逾越节
There will be no Passover.
整个城市实行宵禁
I will put this city under curfew.
我说得够明白了吗
Do I make myself absolutely clear?
你们的父只有一位，就是天上的父。
You only have one Father, and he is in heaven.
你们的导师只有一位，就是默西亚.
You only have one Teacher, and he is the Christ.
就是那个人  那儿
That man, there.
他想要帮助我们
He wants to help us.
他可能会有用
That could be useful.
犹达斯
Judas.
你们找他有什么事
What do you want with him?
就是谈谈
Just a talk.
这是我死前我们在一起的
This is our last meal together,
最后一餐了
before I die.
宽恕我
Spare me.
叛徒
Traitor.
快跑
Run!
-耶稣被抓了  -被抓了  在晚上被抓了
- Jesus has been arrested.  - Arrested? At night?
如果他真的是人们所说的那个人呢
What if he really is what they say he is?
判决结果只有一个
There is only one verdict,
处死
the sentence is death.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!